<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A particular charge or impeachment in the name of His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the army under his command against Denzill Hollis Esquire, Sir Phil: Stapleton, Sir William Lewis, Sir John Clotworthy, Sir William Waller, Sir Iohn Maynard, Knights, Major Generall Massie, Iohn Glynne, Esquire, Recorder of London, VValter Long, Esquire, Col. Edward Harley, &amp; Ant: Nicholl, Esquire, Members of the Honourable House of Commons. By the appointment of his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Councell of Warre. Signed, Iohn Rushworth, Secret.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E741A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220515</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895605</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895605</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153192</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84440)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153192)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2353:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A particular charge or impeachment in the name of His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the army under his command against Denzill Hollis Esquire, Sir Phil: Stapleton, Sir William Lewis, Sir John Clotworthy, Sir William Waller, Sir Iohn Maynard, Knights, Major Generall Massie, Iohn Glynne, Esquire, Recorder of London, VValter Long, Esquire, Col. Edward Harley, &amp; Ant: Nicholl, Esquire, Members of the Honourable House of Commons. By the appointment of his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Councell of Warre. Signed, Iohn Rushworth, Secret.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8, 7-13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the yeare, MDCXLVII. [1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Holles, Denzil Holles, --  Baron, 1599-1680 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Expulsion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Impeachments --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153192:1"/>
            <p>A Particular Charge OR IMPEACHMENT <hi>IN THE NAME OF</hi> HIS EXCELLENCY Sir Thomas Fairfax, And the ARMY under His COMMAND; Againſt
<hi>Denzill Hollis</hi> Eſquire, Sir <hi>Phil: Stapleton,</hi> Sir
<hi>William Lewis,</hi> Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Maynard,</hi> Knights, Major Generall <hi>Maſsie, Iohn Glynne,</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, Recorder of London, <hi>VValter Long,</hi> Eſquire, Col. <hi>Edward Harley,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ant: Nicholl,</hi> Eſquire, Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Honourable Houſe of <hi>Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the appointment of his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and the Councell of Warre.</p>
            <p>Signed, <hi>Iohn Ruſhworth,</hi> Secret.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Yeare, MDCXLVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="charge">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153192:2"/>
            <head>A PARTICVLAR CHARGE OR IMPEACHMENT In the Name of his Excellency Sir THO: FAIRFAX, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>VVHereas on the fifteenth day of June laſt. the Heads of a Charge were delivered in the name of the ſaid Army, unto the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of Parliament, to be ſent up to the Parliament, againſt the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons above-named. Now in proſecution and maintenance thereof, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the power thereby preſerved; It is in the Name of the ſaid Army more particularly charged againſt the ſaid perſons as followeth:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the ſaid Mr. <hi>Denzill Hollis</hi> during the late Warre in proſecution of the evill deſignes expreſſed in the generall Heads or Articles formerly exhibited, contrary to the truſt repoſed in him, contrary to his oath taken in June 1643. and contrary to the Ordinance of Parliament, dated in Oct. 1643. hath aſſiſted the King in the late unnaturall Warre, and held corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency and intelligence with the Enemy againſt the Parliament in manner following, <hi>(viz.)</hi> He the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> being one of the ſpeciall Commiſſioners for the Parliament, to preſent Propoſitions of both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the King at Oxford, did privately and contrary to his inſtructions, at ſeverall times make his addreſſes unto the Kings party there then in Armes againſt the Parliament, namely unto the Earle of <hi>Lyndſey,</hi> the Earle of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153192:2"/> 
               <hi>Southampton,</hi> the Lord <hi>Savill,</hi> and others, and did ſecretly plot and adviſe them againſt the Parliament, and did intimate unto them, or one of them, that the ſaid propoſitions then ſent unto his Majeſty by the Parl. were unreaſonable. And the ſaid M.
<hi>Hollis</hi> being demanded what anſwer he would adviſe the King to make to the ſaid Propopoſitions, he the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> did adviſe, that the King ſhould demand a Treaty however, and then declare how unreaſonable the Propoſitions were; and that yet for the peace of the Kingdome, His Majeſty would treat upon them, but withall wiſhed the ſaid Treaty might bee in London, whither the King himſelfe ſhould come upon ſecurity. Hee the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> adding, that there was nothing in the world, that the violent party (meaning the well-affected party to the Parliament againſt the Enemy) did ſo much feare, as His Majeſties comming to London, which would be a certaine diſſolution of their authority and power. And the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> bad thoſe ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or one of them, aſſure the King, that if His Majeſty knew as much as he (the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi>) knew, His Majeſty would take his horſe and be at London the next day, or words to that effect. And it being againe demanded, whether (if the King ſhould be willing to come) it would be accepted of, He the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> thereto anſwered, that certainly it would be much oppoſed; but yet he the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> was confident, that he and his party (meaning ſome of the Members above-named, and others) ſhould carry it, and wiſhed the King to put it upon that triall. And the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> was deſired by the ſaid Earle of
<hi>Lyndſey,</hi> Earle of <hi>Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and Lord <hi>Savill,</hi> or one of them, that he would be pleaſed to draw ſuch an Anſwer in writing to the ſaid Propoſitions, as hee deſired the King ſhould ſend, and the ſaid Earle of <hi>Southampton</hi> (who was that night to lie in the Kings Bedchamber) would perſwade the King to condiſcend unto it, and thereupon the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> withdrew, and either the ſame day, or the next day following, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> accordingly carried in his hand, unto the ſaid Lords, or one of them, a Paper ready written, which (as he ſaid) was ſuch an Anſwer to the ſaid Propoſitions as he had drawne for the King to ſend to the Parliament, which was taken by the ſaid Lords, or one of them, and carried to the King, to be conſidered of, and ſo much thereof as adviſed the Kings comming to London was laid by, (the King fearing to adventure himſelfe:) but the reſt of the ſaid Paper the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> (who writ the Kings Anſwer to the ſaid Propoſitions) made uſe of in the ſame words as the ſaid M.
<hi>Hollis</hi> had ſet downe; And the ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Hollis</hi> to ingratiate himſelfe with the Kings partie, did about the ſame time revile the well-affected Members of the Houſe of Commons, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring unto the ſaid Kings partie at <hi>Oxford,</hi> or ſome of them, that thoſe wel-affected
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153192:3"/> Members (which to render them the more odious as he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, he named the violent <hi>Independent</hi> partie) had ill intentions and great averſneſſe to Peace, and that nothing would be more pleaſing to them, then for the King to refuſe the Propoſitions, how unreaſonable ſoever the ſame were, and he alſo then ſaid, that the Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> were very weary of that violent partie, and that they being deſperate to eſtabliſh their <hi>Presbytery</hi> here as in <hi>Scotland,</hi> made their addreſſes to him the ſaid M.
<hi>Hollis</hi> and his partie. All which tended to the protracting of the ſaid late Warre, and to the hindrance of an happy Peace, and the ſaid M.
<hi>Hollis</hi> did alſo after that receive from the Earle of
<hi>Lyndſey</hi> a Letter written in white Inke, concerning ſome ſecret deſigne, and kept it from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Houſe, from
<hi>February</hi> till about <hi>Iuly</hi> after, when it was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by him that brought it: but the Letter it ſelfe was by the ſaid M.
<hi>Hollis</hi> (after hee had read it) burnt. And the ſaid Earle of
<hi>Lyndſey</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the King for a Paſſe for the ſaid M.
<hi>Hollis</hi> to goe to <hi>Oxford:</hi> but the King refuſed to grant it, ſaying, That <hi>Hollis</hi> did him better ſervice in the Parliament, then he could doe him at <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the ſaid Mr <hi>Hollis</hi> and ſir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> during the ſaid late War (when the ſaid Earle of
<hi>Lyndſey</hi> went from the Tower of <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Oxford</hi>) ſent ſeverall Meſſages of intelligence to the Earle of
<hi>Dorſet,</hi> and Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> thereby aſſuring them, that they, the ſaid Mr <hi>Hollis</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> did better ſervice for the King here in Parliament, then they could doe him if they were at <hi>Oxford.</hi> And the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> deſired that the ſaid E. of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> would preſerve him and the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip</hi> and his friends, in the good opinion of the party at
<hi>Oxford</hi> (which was then the K ngs Garriſon) and he the ſaid Sir
<hi>Philip</hi> would do as much for his Lordſhip, and his friends here with the Parliament. And the ſaid Mr <hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> the more to ingratiate themſelves into the favour of the enemy, did of their owne accord without any direction of the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, draw up other Propoſitions then thoſe mentioned in the precedent Articles, which they affirmed were in their Judgements fit for the King to grant, and for the Parliament to deſire, and being ſo drawn up, ſent them privately to his Majeſty, without any authority of Parliament to warrant the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the ſaid Mr <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Sir
<hi>William Waller,</hi> Sir <hi>John Maynard,</hi> Major Generall
<hi>Maſſie,</hi> Mr <hi>Glyn,</hi> Mr <hi>Long,</hi> Collonel <hi>Edward Harley,</hi> and <hi>Anthony Nicholls</hi> in the Months of <hi>March, Aprill, May,</hi> and <hi>June</hi> laſt paſt, and at other times in proſecution of the evill deſignes in the ſeverall generall heads mentioned,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153192:3"/> have frequently aſſembled and met together at the Lady
<hi>Carliles</hi> Lodgings in White-Hall, and in other places with diverſe other perſons diſaffected to the State (without any authority of Parliament) for holding correſpondency with the Queene of <hi>England</hi> now in <hi>France</hi> and her participants, with an intent by ſuch ſecret &amp; clandeſtine treaties amongſt themſelves to put con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions upon the Parliament, and to bring in the King upon their owne tearmes, and having a great power upon the Treaſure of the Kingdome, have therewith maintained and encouraged by Penſions, and otherwiſe, the Queenes Party in
<hi>France,</hi> thereby to beget a ſecond and more bloudy War in this Kingdome, and they, or ſome, or one of them aſſured the Queene 40000.
<abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>per annum,</hi> if She would aſſiſt them in their deſigne, and that they would do more for the King then the Army would do, and that they would find out ſome meanes to deſtroy the Army and their friends.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That in further purſuance of the ſame evill deſignes, they the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Sir <hi>VVilliam Lewis,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy,</hi> Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> and Major Generall <hi>Maſſie,</hi> by the combination aforeſaid, within the ſpace of three months laſt paſt without any authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, invited the <hi>Scots</hi> and other forraigne forces to come into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in a Hoſtile manner, to abet and aſſiſt them in the proſecuting and effecting of their ſaid deſignes. And the ſaid Mr <hi>Hollis</hi> very lately ſent to the ſaid Queene of England then and ſtill in <hi>France,</hi> adviſing her amongſt other things ſpeedily to ſend the Prince into Scotland to march into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the head of an Army. And did ſend a ſpeciall Meſſenger to her for ſuch ends and purpoſes. And the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Sir <hi>VVilliam Lewis,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy,</hi> Sir
<hi>William Waller,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> Mr <hi>Glyn,</hi> Major generall <hi>Maſſie,</hi> Mr <hi>Long,</hi> Collonell <hi>Edward Harley,</hi> and <hi>Anthony Nicholls,</hi> have underhand, of their owne accord without authority of Parliament, liſted, or cauſed, or procured to be liſted divers Commanders and Souldiers, endeavouring thereby to leavy, and raiſe a new War in this Kingdom to protect themſelves in their unjuſt oppreſſions and factious deſignes, and have at ſeverall times within the ſpace of two Months laſt paſt invited, incouraged, abetted and counſelled multitudes of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mado Officers and Souldiers and other rude perſons tumultuouſly and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently to gather together at
<hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to affright and aſſault the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament in their paſſage to and from the Houſe, to offer violence to the Houſe it ſelfe, locking the doore thereof upon them, and ſo impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and by ſuch violences, out-rages and threats to awe and enforce the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> and Mr <hi>Glyn</hi> have been <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153192:4"/> and are obſtructers and prejudgers of ſeverall Petitions to the Parliament for redreſſe of publique grievances, and the ſaid Maſter <hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> in the Month of <hi>May</hi> laſt paſt, did abuſe and affront divers Petitioners, who in a peaceble manner then attended the Committee, whereof Collonell <hi>Lee</hi> was Chaireman; not only reviling and reproaching them, but violently haleing, and boyſterouſly aſſaulting them, and offered to draw their ſwords upon Major
<hi>Tuleday,</hi> and others of the ſaid Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and without any authority or power committed <hi>Nicholas Tew</hi> one of the Petitioners; and ſoone afterwards by the procurement of the ſaid Mr <hi>Hollis</hi> and Sir
<hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> and upon their miſ-information to the Houſe, the ſaid Major <hi>Tuleday,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Tewe,</hi> were impriſoned, not being permitted to ſpeake for themſelves, and the ſaid Maſter
<hi>Glyn</hi> about three moneths ſince, cauſed the ſaid <hi>Nicholas Tewe</hi> to be impriſoned in <hi>Newgate,</hi> and to be detained a long time there, for no other cauſe, but for having a Petition about him, which was to be preſented to the Houſe.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the ſaid Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Sir
<hi>VVilliam VValler,</hi> and Major Generall <hi>Maſſie</hi> have lately in proſecution of the ſaid deſignes in the ſaid generall heads mentioned; againſt the knowne Lawes of this Realme, and rules and Articles of Warre made by Parliament; by an Arbitrary power, impriſoned ſome Members of the Army without any authority, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly Enſigne <hi>Nicholas,</hi> whoſe Pockets they without authority, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be ſearched, and ſeverall Papers to be taken from him, contrary to the liberty of every Subject, and cauſed him to bee ſent a Priſoner from the head Quarters to
<hi>London,</hi> without the authority or privity of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, or the chiefe Officers of the Army commanding in his abſence.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That in or about the Moneth of March laſt, (there being a Petition intended from the Officers and Souldiers of the Army to their Generall (for ſuch things onely as were juſtly due unto them, and concerning them meerely as Souldiers) The ſaid Sir <hi>VVilliam VValler,</hi> Sir <hi>John Clotwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Edward Harley</hi> a Member of the Army, having gotten into their hands a Copy of the ſaid Petition) by combination with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Members above mentioned, with an intent to abuſe the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament into prejudices and jealouſies againſt the proceedings of the Army concerning the ſaid Petition (they well knowing that the ſaid Army ſtood in their way, and hindreth them from bringing to paſſe the deſignes in the ſaid generall Charges expreſſed) did falſely and malitiouſly informe the Houſe, That the ſaid Petition was contrived and promoted to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch and diſoblige the Army from the Parliament; And that it was managed and carried on by divers principall Officers in the Army, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153192:4"/> orders were given out for the reading of it in the head of every Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and whoſoever would not ſubſcribe it, ſhould bee put out of the Muſters, and caſhiered the Army, and by thoſe and other aggravations did repreſent it to the Houſe as a deſigne againſt the Parliament; further adding that ſome Regiments which were remote, were ſent for, to joyne with the reſt of the Army for that purpoſe; by which miſ-informations they the ſaid Members did the ſame day procure a peremptory Order to the Generall, to ſuppreſſe the ſaid Petition.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That ſome few dayes after, Colonell <hi>Edward Harley</hi> by the Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation aforeſaid, and in purſuance of the ſame deſignes, did produce to the Houſe a Letter ſuppoſed to be written from within the Quarters of the Army, to him the ſaid Colonell <hi>Harley,</hi> by a perſon not named, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it was informed that Colonell <hi>Harleys</hi> Lieutenant Colonell had drawne his Regiment to a rendezvous, and had cauſed the ſaid Petition to be read at the head of it, and that he threatned to caſhiere and put out of the Muſters all that would not ſubſcribe it, and that the deſigne of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my therein was to enſlave the Parliament and Kingdome, (if the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment proceeded not to ſome High Reſolution) or to that effect, as by the ſaid Letter (relation thereunto being had) may appeare; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſubſtance of the ſaid Letter was moſt untrue, and no author thereof appeared, nor could be produced, although a Committee was appointed for examination thereof, and it was much preſſed the author ſhould be diſcovered; yet the ſaid Colonell <hi>Harley,</hi> Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> did ſo avow the reality of the ſaid Letter, and that the contents thereof would bee made good, as that thereby, and by other falſe ſuggeſtions of theirs againſt the Army, they procured the Houſe (upon a long debate, which held till about eight of the clock at night) to order that a Committee of five Members (whereof the ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Hollis</hi> was one) ſhould prepare a Declaration to bee brought in to the Houſe the next morning ſignifying the Houſes diſlike of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Army upon that Petition as by the ſaid Order dated <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> laſt, may appeare.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="declaration">
                        <p>Upon which ſetling of the ſaid buſineſſe for that night, moſt of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers departed, as conceiving nothing would be done thereupon till the next day, and that then they might have a free debate concerning the ſame; But the Houſe ſtill continuing to ſit (upon diſpatch of ſome Letters formerly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered,) the ſaid Maſter
<hi>Hollis,</hi> by the ſame combination and in further proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153192:5"/> of the ſaid evill deſignes having of himſelfe (without the Committee) prepared a Declaration againſt the Petition it ſelfe, contrary to the intention and direction of the ſaid order, and contrary to the rules of Juſtice and uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all courſe of Parliament, did the ſame night about ten of the clocke, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſurpriſe the Houſe, preſent the ſame Declaration to the Houſe (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſaid Petitioners were, without being heard) declared Enemies to the State, and obſtructers of the reliefe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> if they perſiſted therein (as by the ſame Declaration, relation being thereunto had may appeare) and did procure it to be then paſſed accordingly, to the great diſ-honour of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and their proceedings, to the inſufferable injury, the juſt provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diſcouragement and diſcontent of the Army, to the trouble and danger of the whole Kingdome, to the hindring of the reliefe of
<hi>Ireland,</hi> and other the evill conſequences in the ſaid generall Charges expreſſed.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p n="9">9. That by the ſame and the like falſe informations and ſuggeſtions, the ſaid Colonell <hi>Harley</hi> (then a Member of the Army) Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> and the ſaid other perſons did ſhortly after the ſaid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration ſo made as aforeſaid, procure divers eminent and faithfull Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Army, namely Lieutenant Generall <hi>Hamond,</hi> Colonell <hi>Hamond,</hi> Colonell
<hi>Lilburne,</hi> Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Pride,</hi> and others, to be all ſent for from their Charges in the Army, to appeare at the Barre of the Houſe to make anſwer in relation to the ſaid Petition, againſt whom when they came thither, they could Charge or prove nothing at all, in ſo much as the Houſe thought fit immediately to diſcharge them. And whereas there was a Committee appointed to examine and conſider of the truth or falſhood of them; and the ſaid Members informing, were appointed to produce their proofes and evidence to the ſame before the Committee; though they have ſince then beene often urged, called upon, and demanded to produce their proofes and evidence thereto (if they had any) and have beene plainly told, that if they did not proceed effectually to doe it, they ſhould be accounted the authors and deviſers of the ſaid falſehoods, and reparation would accordingly be demanded againſt them; <hi>Yet they have not to this day produced any proofes or evidence to any of the ſaid informations or ſuggeſtions, whereby the Parliament and Army were ſo much abuſed as before is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: nor could they or any of them be hitherto perſwaded to give in to the ſaid Committee any Charge againſt the ſaid Officers of the Army, which they have then or ſince procured to be ſent for as aforeſaid, but have held di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of them in a long and chargeable attendance upon the Houſe, without any thing layd to their Charge, untill the Houſe was pleaſed to diſcharge them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153192:5"/>X. That the ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hollis,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Phillip Stapleton,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Lewis,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Waller,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Maſſie,</hi> in further pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the deſignes mentioned in the generall heads charged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, have been great Inſtruments in the obſtructing of the Relief of <hi>Ireland; and within the ſpace of two Moneths laſt paſt, did falſly informe the Houſe, that by their procurement there were fifty Companies of Foot, and ten Troops of Horſe of this Army, engaged for</hi> Ireland, <hi>upon the termes, and under the conduct then by the Parliament propounded: and the more to delude the Parliament herein, they, or ſome of them by the combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aforeſaid, did procure divers Officers then in this Army, namely, Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell</hi> Butler, <hi>Lievtenant-colonell</hi> Jackſon,
<hi>Major</hi> Gooday, <hi>and others, to give in their Names, as listing themſelves for</hi> Ireland <hi>(on the ſaid termes, and conduct propounded) when as thoſe Officers did at the ſame time declare themſelves unwilling thereunto, and reſolved not to goe ſerve in</hi> Ireland <hi>on any termes whatſoever; they the ſaid Members underhand aſſuring them, that though they make uſe of their names, yet they ſhould not goe for that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: They have likewiſe untruly informed the houſe, and given in the names of many conſiderable Officers of the Army, namely, Captaine</hi> Pennifather <hi>and Captaine</hi> Burges, <hi>of Colonell</hi> Butler's <hi>Regiment; Capt.</hi> Clark, <hi>and four or more Commiſſion-Officers of Sir</hi> Hardreſſe Waller's <hi>Regiment, and others, as having been ſubſcribed for</hi> Ireland, <hi>who did not ſo engage or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, nor give any conſent thereto, but did then, and have ever ſince utterly diſavowed the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And about the ſame time they alſo reported to the Houſe the name and offer of Lievt. Col. <hi>Farrington,</hi> as being then a Lievt. Col. of this Army, and engaging for himſelf and his Regiment for
<hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whereas the ſaid <hi>Farrington</hi> had been caſheered the Army a yeer and a half before; by which and other their falſe informations and reports of that nature, the Parliament was abuſed and miſled into a conceit and confidence of a ſtrength out of the Army, then ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be engaged, and ready for <hi>Ireland</hi> on their own termes, when as in truth the ſame was but a meer deluſion, and which was ſo contrived on purpoſe to occaſion a ſlighting and neglecting of the Army, as ſuppoſing no further uſe for them.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. Whereas part of three Regiments of Foot, <hi>viz.</hi> Col. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert's,</hi> Col. <hi>Kemp's,</hi> and Col. <hi>Gray's,</hi> were by order of the Houſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced towards the relief of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as farre as <hi>Broomſgrave</hi> in the County of <hi>Worcester,</hi> the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Phillip Stapleton,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hollis,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Lewis,</hi> and Major Gen.
<hi>Maſſie,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> 
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153192:6"/> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               <hi>Glyn,</hi> by combination aforeſaid, did of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord without the knowledge or direction of the Houſe, on the ſixt day of <hi>June</hi> laſt, being Sabbith day, without ſummoning a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, command thoſe Forces back again as far as <hi>Redding,</hi> with an evil intent to draw Forces together, to beget a new war in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">XII. That the ſaid Sr <hi>John Clotworthy</hi> in proſecution of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes in the ſaid generall charges expreſſed, hath in the yeer 1642 1643, 1644. and ſince, converted ſeverall great ſums of Money (which by ſeverall Orders of Parliaments and of the
<hi>Iriſh</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee were deſigned for the relief of <hi>Ireland</hi>) to his owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar uſe, namely, the ſum of 280. <abbr>l.</abbr> which by order of both Houſes dated the 11. of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1642. was to be paid for 20. Buts of Sack for <hi>Ireland,</hi> 700 <abbr>l.</abbr> which the ſame day was Ordered for 2000. ſwords, 300 <abbr>l.</abbr> which was by Order of the ſaid <hi>Iriſh</hi> Committee dated the 5. of <hi>Apr.</hi> 1643. was deſigned for 120. pair of Piſtols; and divers other ſums of Money upon ſeverall other Orders, which he, the ſaid Sr <hi>John Clotworthy</hi> from time to time received for the uſe and relief of <hi>Irel.</hi> but were not imployed to the uſes by the ſaid Orders intended and directed, but to his, the ſaid Sr <hi>John Chotworthies</hi> own private uſe as aforeſaid; and that he hath within two yeers laſt paſt received ſeverall ſums of Money, Armes and other proviſions for a Troop of Horſe, which he pretended he had raiſed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> when as he had not, nor did raiſe or furniſh any ſuch Troop as he pretended; and that he, the ſaid Sr <hi>John Clotworthy</hi> for money and other rewards, hath preferred <hi>John Davis</hi> and <hi>William Sommers,</hi> and others, to be entruſted with the
<hi>Iriſh</hi> affaires, who have kept cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency with the enemy, and have defrauded the ſtate of other great ſums of Money, and he hath been privy to, and a ſharer in ſuch their actions.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. That about <hi>Nov.</hi> laſt paſt, the ſaid Sr
<hi>Joh. Clotworthy,</hi> being by the Parl. ſent a Commiſſioner with others into <hi>Irel.</hi> who all had a joint power and authority to treat w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the Earl of <hi>Ormond</hi> for the ſpace of four days and no more; he the ſaid Sr <hi>Jo. Clotworthy,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ſpeciall truſt repoſed in him, held ſecret intelligence with the ſaid E. of
<hi>Ormond</hi> by cipher or character, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or knowledge of thoſe others in commiſſion w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> him, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weeks after the time ſo limited was expired, &amp; about the ſame time, he the ſaid Sr <hi>Jo. Clotworthy</hi> held ſecret intelligence w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>George</hi> L.
<hi>Digby,</hi> then in <hi>Irel.</hi> beyond the time prefixed, &amp; without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153192:6"/> of the ſaid other Commiſſioners: and in order thereunto, the ſaid <hi>Ormond</hi> and <hi>Digby</hi> lately imployed one <hi>Slingsby</hi> to come into this Kingdom about a deſign co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the
<hi>Prince,</hi> as he pretendeth.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. That the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>J. Clotworthy,</hi> M.
<hi>Hollis,</hi> S. <hi>Phil. Stapleton,</hi> by combination with the reſt of the Members before named, in further proſecution of the deſigns beforementioned, wel knowing that the L. <hi>Lyle,</hi> late Preſident of
<hi>Irel.</hi> was both faithfull and vigilant while he was truſted in the ſame Kingdom, and had now this laſt Spring made proviſions ready to march into the field, &amp; that the L. Baron of <hi>Brohil</hi> Gen. of the Parl<hi rend="sup">s</hi> Horſe in <hi>Munſter,</hi> &amp; Col. Sr <hi>Arthur Loftus,</hi> perſons of honor and reputation, and of great fortunes in the ſaid Kingdom, lately came purpoſely into this Kingd. to exhibit, &amp; did exhibit many Articles of high treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the L. <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying the Parlia<hi rend="sup">s</hi> Army to the Enemy (as formerly he had done) yet by the great power and violent interpoſition of the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>J. Clotworthy,</hi> M.
<hi>Hollis,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Phil. Stapleton,</hi> by the practice and combinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aforeſaid, the ſaid Articles have been obſtructed, and the buſineſſe not ſuffered to come to a hearing, and the ſaid L.
<hi>Liſle</hi> haſtily called out of <hi>Irel.</hi> and the the power and command of the Parl. forces in that Kingdom committed to the ſaid L.
<hi>Inchiquin</hi> to the loſſe of this Summer ſervice, and the expence of much Treaſure for new prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: and whereas the ſaid L.
<hi>Liſle</hi> being ſo ſuddenly called fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence as aforeſaid, did deſign and depute, S. <hi>Hardreſſe Waller,</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Major Gen. of the Forces there (a man of known integrity and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage both for his ſervice in
<hi>Eng.</hi> &amp; <hi>Irel.</hi> and of conſiderable fortunes there) to take care of the ſaid L. <hi>Liſles</hi> Forces, till the pleaſure of the Parl. may be further known; but the ſaid L. <hi>Inchiquin</hi> upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of a Letter from the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>J. Clotworthy,</hi> M.
<hi>Hollis,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Phil. Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> or one of them (or from ſome other perſon by their, or one of their direction, privity or procurement) did expreſſe that he had order or direction from <hi>London,</hi> that no man that favoured the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents (under which name the ſaid Lord of
<hi>Inchequin</hi> hath comprehended all men that have ſhewed themſelves oppoſite to Tyranny and Arbitrary Government) ſhould have any truſt or command there. Nay, although they were of another judgment, yet if they would not proſecute the Independents, they ſhould not be imployed there, or words to that effect. And under colour thereof, the ſaid <hi>Hardreſſe Waller,</hi> and all others that had their Commiſſions from the ſaid Lord
<hi>Liſle,</hi> while he commanded were diſplaced, to the diſcouragement of thoſe and other faithfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the Parliament, and to the great diſſervice and hazard of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="15">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153192:7"/>XV. That whereas a Committee of the Houſe of Commons hath been lately appointed by the Parliament to conſider of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions for the ſetling and preſervation of <hi>Wales,</hi> whereof the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> and Mr <hi>Glyn</hi> were and are Members, and to report the ſame to the Houſe, They the ſaid Sir
<hi>William Lewis</hi> and Maſter <hi>Glyn</hi> with others of the ſaid Committee did on the 13 day of <hi>April</hi> now laſt paſt, without any authority of Parliament, before any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port made to the Houſes, of their owne accord, in ſtead of ſetling and preſerving <hi>Wales,</hi> order that all Committees for Sequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould forbeare all proceedings of Sequeſtrations againſt all or any the Inhabitants of <hi>Wales.</hi> And although ſome few perſons were (upon generall heads) excepted; yet by vertue of that illegal Order, all he Commiſſioners of Peace, Commiſſioners of Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (though never ſo active in preſſing men, and raiſing money for Forces againſt the Parliament) all the Commiſſioners of Array that did or ſhould at any time come in and ſubmit to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or their Commanders in Chief, all that had born armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, unleſſe they were Governours or other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of War that held ſome Town, Caſtle, or Fort againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; all diſaffected and ſcandalous Miniſters, though in their Sermons they uſually reviled and ſcandalized the Parliament and their proceedings, calling them Rebels and Traitors; and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incenſing the People againſt the Parliament, but uſually taking up Armes, and leading their Pariſhioners in arms upon any Alarum againſt the Parliament; and many other deſperate Delinquents have been, and ſtill are taken off and freed from Sequeſtration: and the ſaid Order was ſent to every ſeverall Committee in <hi>Wales,</hi> in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Letters from the ſaid Committee, contrary to ſeveral Orders and Ordinances of Parliament, and contrary to the Rules of juſtice and equity which ſhould impartially be adminiſtred as wel in <hi>Wales</hi> as in other places of this Kingdom, whereby the ill affected Gentry and Miniſtry of that Country are grown ſo high and inſolent, that honeſt men dare ſcarce live amongſt them: ſo as that which was intended by the Parliament to ſettle and preſerve <hi>Wales,</hi> is by the practice of the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> and Maſter
<hi>Glyn</hi> perverted to the danger and deſtruction of it.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. That the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> and Mr.
<hi>Glyn</hi> have further ingratiated themſelves with the Delinquents of
<hi>Wales,</hi> and prepared, them for their ſaid deſignes, in manner following; <hi>viz.</hi> he the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> hath within two yeers laſt paſt countenanced and protected many of the moſt notorious &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous Delinque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153192:7"/> the ſeveral Countries of <hi>South-Wales;</hi> namely the L. of <hi>Carbery,</hi> &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in
<hi>Carmarthinſh.</hi> Mr <hi>Crane</hi> and others in
<hi>Glamorganſhire,</hi> Mr <hi>Morgan</hi> late Knight of the ſhire, Mr
<hi>John Herbert</hi> and others in <hi>Brecknockſhire,</hi> Mr
<hi>Gwyn,</hi> Mr <hi>Lewis,</hi> &amp; divers others in
<hi>Radnorſhire,</hi> by freeing ſome of them altogether from Compoſitions, though ſequeſtred, by laboring divers Members of the Houſe &amp; of Comittees to be favourable in compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with others, and to admit of ſuch to their Compoſitions as were uncapable thereof. And the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Lewis</hi> hath animated &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged ſome of the ſaid perſons to continue their fidelity unto the Kings cauſe, promiſing them, That if they would be friends with the King for him, he and his would be their friends in the Parliament: in ſo much as his friends the Delinquents in thoſe parts have lately look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon him as a riſing man when the King ſhall come to <hi>London;</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> hath lately been their conſtant boaſting. And the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is</hi> hath within two yeers laſt paſt cauſed divers that hath been Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for the King, and had preſt men, and raiſed moneys to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the late War againſt the Parliament, namely, his Brother Maſt. <hi>Tho. Lewis,</hi> Mr <hi>Gwyn,</hi> Mr <hi>Charles Walhiffe,</hi> Mr <hi>Meridith Lewis,</hi> Mr <hi>Edward Williams,</hi> and many others to be Commiſſioners of the Peace, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee-men for the ſaid County of <hi>Brecknock,</hi> inſomuch as thoſe that have been moſt active and faithfull to the Parliament, have been and ſtill are out-voted in thoſe places, and can do no conſiderable ſervice for the Parliament: and the rather for that the ſaid Sir
<hi>William Lewis</hi> hath alſo produced one <hi>Edward Williams</hi> his owne kinſman, and much diſaffected to the Parliament, to be Sollicitor of Sequeſtrations in that County, who is and hath been very remiſſe &amp; corrupt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> hath by the means aforeſaid late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly procured Maſter <hi>Edward Lewis</hi> his ſonne, though unfit for that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, to be choſen and returned Burgeſſe for
<hi>Brecknoe;</hi> which that he might the better effect, he kept the Writ for election of the ſaid Burgeſſe above eight moneths in his owne cuſtodie before it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Sheriffe of the ſaid County. And likewiſe that the ſaid Maſter <hi>John Glyn</hi> with in two years laſt paſt hath procured ſeverall perſons that have lately been Comiſſioners of Array, and in Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament in <hi>Northwales,</hi> (viz.)
<gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and others to be named in the Commiſſion of the peace for the Counties of <hi>Denbigh</hi> &amp; <hi>Carnarvan,</hi> &amp; other Counties there, &amp; to be put in other great places of Truſt &amp; Command there, &amp; amongſt others, Col. <hi>Glyn</hi> his brother, who was lately a Colonel in the Kings Army, is by the ſaid Mr <hi>John Glyns</hi> procurement become Governor of the Town &amp; Caſtle of <hi>Carnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van,</hi> &amp; Admiral or Vice-Admirall of the Iriſh ſeas, to the endangering
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> countries lying upon the coaſts towards Ireland, &amp; to the fear
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="17">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:153192:8"/>XVII. That the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> being heretofore (during theſe troubles) Governor of Portſmouth, a Garriſon for the Parliament, in which time he received much of the Publick Treaſure, for which he hath not yet given an Accompt, did while he was Governor there, frequently hold correſpondency and intelligence with the Kings party, about the delivery up of the ſaid Garriſon; inſomuch as although Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> and divers others in that Garriſon were proclaimed Traitors to the King, yet he by the Kings ſpeciall Command was ſpared, the King affirming, That the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> was his Friend, and that he was confident he would do h m good ſervice, or to that effect. And although the then was a Parliament-man, and Governor of Portſmouth, as aforeſaid, and his eſtate in the ſaid County of Breck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nock, being of the value of aboue ſix hundred pound <hi>per annum,</hi> was three years in the Kings quarters, yet the ſame was never ſequeſtred: And ſince the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath prevailed, Colonel <hi>Herbert Price</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> having been Governor of Breck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nock for the King againſt the Parliament, being ſequeſtred, the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> by his ſollicitations to the Committee, procured the perſonall Eſtate of the ſaid Colonel <hi>Price,</hi> which the Committee of the County had found out, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be brought to <hi>Morgan Awbrayes</hi> houſe in Brecknock, to be reſtored unto him, without any ſatisfaction to the State, and hath procured his the ſaid Col. <hi>Prices</hi> lands in the ſaid County of Brecknock, being worth about three hundred pound <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> to be let to a friend of the ſaid Col. <hi>Pr ces,</hi> to his wives uſe, as fifty pound <hi>per annum,</hi> contrary to the directions of ſeverall Ordinances of Parliament made in that behalf.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. That the ſaid Mr <hi>Iohn Glyn,</hi> or ſome other perſon or perſons, by his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, conſent, or privity, or to his uſe, hath (during his being a Member of the Houſe of Commons) taken rewards of ſeverall perſons for ſervice done them in the Houſe, as namely amongſt others, divers Drovers from Wales, who by his means and procurement had an allowance by Order of the Houſe for three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pound, in ſatisfaction of loſſes they had ſuſtained by the Enemy, did pay unto the wife of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Glyn</hi> the ſum of an hundred pound, as a reward for his ſaid ſervice.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. That the ſaid Mr <hi>Iohn Glyn,</hi> as he hath been moſt active to bring into the Commiſſion of Peace, and into other places of Authority, divers notorious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents in North Wales, as aforeſaid, ſo hath been as active, as much as in him lies, to put out and keep out of the <hi>Militia</hi> and Common-Councell of London, and out of the Commiſſion of Peace of Middleſex, many eminent and faithfull men, that have laid out their eſtates, and adventured their lives for defence of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and City, in the time of their greateſt neceſſity; namely, Alderman <hi>Pennington,</hi> Col. <hi>Tiebborn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Eſtwick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Moyer,</hi> and others, contrary to the Declaration of both Kingdoms, which hath aſſured all lawfull favour and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to thoſe that have been faithfull, and ſhall ſo continue to the Parliament: which doings muſt needs tend to the giving a freſh occaſion and power to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt the Parliaments beſt friends, to the diſhonour of the Parliament, and he indangering of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. That the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> M.
<hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Lewis,</hi> have by their power and countenance, as Members of the Houſe Commons, both joyntly and ſeverally, uſed meanes to obſtruct the courſe of Juſtice, and have interpoſed themſelves in ſeverall Cauſes, and by word of mouth moved and perſwaded Judges and other Officers, on the behalf of ſuch as they conceive to be their friends: Amongſt others, whereas a great
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:153192:8"/>
               <hi>Langham</hi> and Captaine <hi>Lymery,</hi> and Counſell was met for the pleading thereof, the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> did repaire to the Earle of <hi>Rutland</hi> about the ſame; and the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> told the ſaid Earle, that they (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe, and the ſaid M. <hi>Hollis, William Lewis</hi>) were fully ſatisfied concerning the juſtice of
<hi>Langhams</hi> Cauſe; and therefore as the ſaid Earle did reſpect them, the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir
<hi>William Lewis,</hi> or expected from them, he the ſaid Earle of
<hi>Rutland</hi> ſhould give his Vote for <hi>Langham,</hi> or uſed words to that effect; which alſo was ſeconded by the ſaid M. <hi>Hollis</hi> in words, and agreed unto by the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> as appeared by his preſence and geſture. And the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> did exerciſe the ſame power in a Cauſe of <hi>Iohn Gunters,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. That the ſaid M. <hi>Anthony Nicholls,</hi> although about four yeares ſince hee was by the Committee of Priviledges voted, that he was not a Member fit to ſit in the Houſe, by reaſon his election was void, yet hee the ſaid M. <hi>Nicholls</hi> doth not only ſit and vote there as a Member, but by his power and threats in the Weſt-Countries, and by his ſollicitations and indirect practiſes, hath brought in or procured to be brought in, about twenty eight Members more out of Cornwall, on purpoſe to carry on the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and practiſes before-mentioned, and to make a faction in the ſaid Houſe: and not withſtanding the ſelfe denying Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, he the ſaid M. <hi>Nicholls</hi> doth ſtill hold a place in the Tower formerly conferred upon him by the Houſe, and receiveth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits thereof to his owne uſe.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. That the ſaid M. <hi>Nicholls,</hi> hath ſince his fitting in the Houſe as aforeſaid, taken rewards for ſervice done there; namely, whereas Sir <hi>William Vuedall</hi> Knight, for deſerting the Parliament and going to Yorke with the King, was ſuſpended the Houſe, hee the ſaid M. <hi>Nicholls</hi> for the ſumme of one hundred pounds, or one hundred fifty pounds, paid unto him or to his uſe, by the ſaid Sir
<hi>William Vuedall</hi> or ſome for him, did by miſ-informations to the Houſe procure the ſaid Sir <hi>William Vuedall</hi> to be re-admitted a Member of the ſaid Houſe, and the ſaid M. <hi>Nicholls</hi> while hee was a Member of the Committee for ſafety, hee and others of the ſaid Committee having iſſued forth a Warrant for ſearching Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich houſe, he the ſaid M. <hi>Nicholls</hi> did under-hand acquaint one of the Queens Officers therewith, and thereby prevented the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of the ſaid Committee, to the great diſſervice of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:153192:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> affaires, did out of covetouſneſſe or unworthineſſe procure a comand of a troops or Horſe under his Excellency the late L. General Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> when ever hi, ſaid Troop came upon any ſervice, he the ſaid M. <hi>Long</hi> out of feare treachery unworthily abſented himſelfe, &amp; never was ſeen or known to charge the enemy in perſon, though his Tropp of en engaged, namely at the battell at Edgehill, when he ſaw there was like to be blows, he the ſaid M.
<hi>Long</hi> left the field, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver charged before his Troop; and at the battell or fight at Brainford, though his Troop were there, yet he ſtaid at London till the danger was paſt, and fighting done; &amp; when his Troop was ſent into the Weſt, he took no other notice, of it, but to receive his pay, and in the mean while he repaired into the County of Eſſex, and procured a Commiſſion to be a Colonel of Horſe, and inſtead of fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliaments enemies, he betook himſelf to plunder, and oppreſſe the Parliaments friends, there, and contarie to Order, and without any Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y or Exigences of War, compelling him thereto, inforced great ſums of money, &amp; many horſes, and other proviſions from the Countrey, namely from M. <hi>Tho. Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> a man well affected, who had the Generalls protection (whoſe horſes were taken from his Plough) and others, to the great loſſes and oppreſſion of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to the great diſhon ur of Parliament, whoſe ſervice he nevertheleſſe neglected, and hath not hitherto given an accompt of the great ſummes of money and other things that he ſo exacted from the Countrey as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. That the ſaid M. <hi>Long</hi> afterwards (upon pretence of ſome loſſes ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the enemy, and ſome great ſervice he had done for the State) did procure of the H uſe a great Office in the Chancery, namely to be the Chiefe Regiſter of that Court, wherein his skill was litle, and whereof he was and ſtill is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uncapable; and although for a time upon the ſelfe denying Ordinance, he, was diſplaced; yet upon the motion, or by the power and meanes of the ſaid M
<hi>Hollis,</hi> he hath obtained the ſame Office, to the great prejudice of skilful Clerks that have bin bred up in the ſame Court, and to the diſſervice of the Common-Wealth, and the diſhonour of the Houſe.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. That the ſaid M. <hi>Long,</hi> on purpoſe to drive on the deſignes in the ſaid generall Charges expreſſed, hath for the ſpace of two years laſt paſt uſually preſſed and urged ſeverall Members to give their Votes ſuch wayes as he pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to that end and purpoſe doth conſtantly place himſelfe neer the doore of the Houſe, that when any debate is concerning any deſigne wherein his party is ingaged, he the ſaid M. <hi>Long</hi> hath uſed much tempering and violence to ſuch of his own party as would goe out of the Houſe, and hath perſwaded them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue there for their Votes, and he the ſaid M.
<hi>Long,</hi> in caſe any ſuch have gone out of the Houſe, hath been very inquiſitive where they may be found, that ſo he may goe for them when the buſineſſe in debate comes neare to be put to the Vote, and when they come not according to his expectation, doth ordinarily run out of the Houſe himſelfe to call them, and drive them in again, that he hath been commonly c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lled (by thoſe that are without the Houſe, and have taken notice of his actions) the
<hi>Parliament-driver,</hi> whereby the freedome of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers is taken from them, the manner of the Parliaments proceedings much ſcandalized, and many times evil and dangerous deſignes drove on in a faction by Votes, to the great prejudice of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>All which matters and things the ſaid Army ſhall and will be ready (in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time) to make good by proof upon Oath, as this honourable Houſe ſhall direct. And for that by reaſon of the ſtraightneſſe of time, and other more weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Affaires of the Army, they could not ſo fully finiſh and compliſh the ſaid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles; therefore the ſaid Army do ſtill reſerve further liberty to add other Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles againſt the ſaid Members, or any of them, at any time before their Triall, as occaſion ſhall ſerve.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
